Settlements Collection, 1883-1972
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Settlements collection
1883-1972
MS 430
4 boxes; 6 volumes (1.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
The Settlements Collection documents the social settlement movement and its contributions to poor and working-class urban communities from the 1880s through the first half of the 20th century. Documentation primarily relates to the College Settlement Association (later called the Intercollegiate Community Service Association), and the individual settlements affiliated with it: the College Settlement of Philadelphia, Denison House in Boston, the Smith Alumnae Chapter, and the Rivington Street Settlement in New York City. Types of material include articles, correspondence, clippings, historical writings, pamphlets, annual reports, minutes, newsletters, and photographs.
The Settlements Collection contains manuscript and printed material that primarily relate to the College Settlement Association, which later became the Intercollegiate Community Service Association, and the individual settlements affiliated with it, primarily the College Settlement of Philadelphia, Denison House in Boston, the Smith Alumnae Chapter, and the Rivington Street Settlement in New York City. The bulk of the material dates from the 1880s, when the settlement movement first emerged in the U.S., to the 1960s when, after the appearance of federal anti-poverty programs, many settlements closed their doors permanently.
The nineteenth century material in this collection includes both published and unpublished sources, such as articles, correspondence, newspaper clippings, promotional pamphlets, histories, and reports that document the emergence and evolution of the settlement movement in the 1880s and 1890s. It also illustrates both settlement founders' efforts to legitimize their work, and their increasingly successful endeavors to draw educated young women into the field of settlement work.
The twentieth century material is more varied and includes articles, commemorative booklets, correspondence, fundraising appeals, minutes, newsletters, pamphlets, photographs, programs, and an unpublished thesis. These items document the thorough institutionalization of settlements in U.S. society between 1900 and the 1930s, the crucial contributions they made to poor and working-class communities, and the gradual decline that most settlements faced in the post-World War II period. The collection includes bound volumes of the annual reports of the College Settlement Association (1890-1913), as well as books and newsletters published by the CSA.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions are expected.
History of the Collection
Materials in this "artificial" subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors. Some items may have been removed from other collections.
Search Terms
College Settlement Association--History--Sources; College Settlement Association. Smith Alumnae Chapter; Intercollegiate Community Service Association--History--Sources; Poor women--United States--History--20th century; Social settlements--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia--History--Sources; Social settlements--Massachusetts--History--Sources; Social settlements--New York (State)--New York--History--Sources; Social settlements--United States--History-Sources; Working class women--United States--History--Sources
- Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
- General: Bibliography of College, University and Social Settlements, and History of the Settlement Movement, 1893-1927 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- College settlements
  - General: clippings and pamphlets, 1899-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Andover House Association (Boston): report, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - College Settlement Association
    - "Cultural Hybrid in the Slums: the College Woman and the Settlement House, 1889-1894," by John P. Rousmaniere, American Quarterly, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Pamphlets, theater scripts, and clipping, 1898-1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Lists of subscribers, 1896-1906 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Quarterly, 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Smith Alumnae Chapter
      - Correspondence, 1915-1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Pamphlets, annual reports, and notebook, 1909-1927 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Intercollegiate Community Service Association (formerly College Settlement Association): annual reports, 1917-1926 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      [see also box 2 and volumes on shelf]
    - College Settlement News (New York), 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - College Settlement of Philadelphia
    - Anna Freeman Davies: book and publications, 1943-1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - General: annual reports, correspondence, photographs, and pamphlets, 1904-1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      [see also volumes on shelf]
    - Photographs, newsletters, annual reports, clippings, and correspondence, 1942-1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - College Settlement Association: annual reports, 1890-1913 (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
    [see also box 1 and volumes on shelf]
  - Dennison House (Boston)
    - General: correspondence, directory, pamphlets, annual reports, and clippings, 1903-1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Annual reports, 1900, 1903, 1907-1915 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Italian Department: reports and pamphlets, 1906-1913 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence
      - George Washington Cable, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Margaret Deland, 1898-1899 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - T.W. Higginson, 1847-1879 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Julia Ward Howe, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Henry Irving, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Julia C. Lathrop, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Richard G. Moulton, 1904 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Katherine A. Sanborn, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Isobel Strong, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Kate Douglas Wiggin-Riggs, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 95 Rivington St. (NYC)
    - The first year at the College Settlement by Jane E. Robbins, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Pamphlets, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Annual reports, 1890, 1899-1900, 1901/1902, 1913/1914 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Industrial settlements (Hartley House, NY): pamphlet, circa 1897 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Music settlements (Third St. Music School): annual reports, pamphlet, and manuscript, 1959-1965 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Social settlements
  - General: pamphlet, articles, and thesis manuscript, 1892-1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Dorothea Dix House (Boston): pamphlets, 1898-1901 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Greenwich House (NYC): annual report (1921), clippings, and pamphlet (re: Mary Simkhovitch), 1921-1952 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Henry St. Settlement (NYC): pamphlet, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Hull House (Chicago): article (Smith College Monthly), 1894 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Social Settlements and the Labor Question: pamphlet, circa 1897 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Volumes on shelf
  - College Settlements Association: annual reports
    [duplicates - see also box 2]
    - 1890-1899 (volumes 1-10)
    - 1900-1906 (volumes 11-17)
    - 1896-1897, 1900-1913
  - College Settlement News and News of the College Settlement of Philadelphia, 1895-1921
  - Reports of the College Settlement of Philadelphia, 1895-1920
  - St. Mary Street Settlement: Library and Settlement, 1886-1895